There's one other thing that I want to talk about, and that is the Python Ripple.
What is a Ripple? Ripple stands for Read Evaluate Print Loop. This is an interactive Python prompt,
where you can type in Python programs, line-by-line, and see results right away.
There are lots and lots of benefits to using a Ripple.
By seeing this instantaneous output, you get instantaneous feedback, which is exactly what you need when
you're learning. You want to fail fast and fail often, make mistakes, experiment.
There is really not much that you can break, so take full advantage of the Ripple.
For the first few chapters we're going to be working exclusively in the Ripple, and I asked
that you type along with me. The downside to the Ripple is you eventually will want to
store your Python code for reuse, and that's what Python files are for and Python programs.
You can consider the Ripple more of a scratch area, so it's where you can experiment and play,
and try out Python code. If you want to save the output of your Ripple, you can just copy and paste
that into a file, which I recommend doing if you want to go back and look at what you were working on.
The Ripple isn't just a tool for beginners. As a Python programmer, I use it all the time.
If I can't remember what a method does, or what the return value of something is,
I pop up a Ripple, and I can quickly answer that question for myself without having to Google,
or Redox, or whatever, so it's not just something that beginners use. It's going to be a tool
that you'll have in your toolkit for the rest of your Python career. Now, you'll know that you're
in a Ripple when you see three arrow lines, those are going to indicate that a line of input was given
at the prompt. If you see three arrows in the example code throughout the course, don't copy them
into your own Ripple. The built-in copy function on this course website should take care of that for you.
Now, comments can start with the pound sign, and comments will be ignored in the Ripple. Both
if they're on a new line, or if they follow a line of code, so you might see me add in some comments
for some context as I type. And then lines that don't start with either of those things
or a dot means that it was output produced by running input from the prompt. So let's try this out.
If you want to open the Ripple on your terminal, without VS code, as long as your virtual environment
is activated, you can type Python, and it will bring it up for you. And you should see these three
arrows, and a blinking prompt letting you know that Python is ready for input. On Mac and Linux
systems, you can exit out of this by hitting Ctrl D. On Windows, I think it's slightly different.
I don't remember the command off-hand, but I'm pretty sure the Ripple prints it out.
Either way, on Linux or Windows systems, if you don't remember how to
quit this Ripple, you can just type exit as a function, and that will exit it for you.
If you don't want to remember the keyboard shortcuts. Now in VS code, we can just pull up the
Ripple from the command palette and have it in our integrated terminal. So to do that,
Ctrl Shift P for Windows, Command Shift P for Mac, and then Python, start Ripple.
And that will bring up the Ripple right in VS code for me.
Now we can start typing some Python code and seeing what happens.
We can type a number and see that the output is just printed out.
We can type a, we can assign a variable. So in this case, I'm going to assign the number five to X.
You'll see here that nothing was printed out, but it's because an assignment was made,
and nothing was returned from that assignment. So in the Ripple, if you want to see the value of
what's an X now, you can just type X by itself, and you'll see that output again.
Once we move to files, and we don't have these handy features of the Ripple, you're going to need to
use the print function in order to see any output. We're going to talk a lot more about print later,
but for the time being, you can just pass a variable to the print function, or you can pass an
a string that is delineated with quotes. And in the Ripple, that'll do the same thing as just typing the variable.
So now you should be all set up to work on the rest of the exercises in this course.
There's a bit of a checklist. If you're missing a step, I recommend that you go back in the break
and make sure that you're all set up. You need to have Python 3.9 installs, need to have the
VS code extension installed, need to have the Python extension for VS code installed, need to have
made a Pi workshop directory in your home folder, and navigated to it, created a virtual environment,
and activated that virtual environment, and open VS code in your project directory.
If you have code on your path, you can just navigate to a directory where you have a virtual
environment opened and type code dot. That will open VS code in this project directory. It should
pick up the virtual environment automatically, but you'll still want to double check.
If you don't have that installed on your path, that's okay. You can just launch VS code
and navigate to the project directory. It's not a prerequisite for the course. It's just a handy shortcut.
And there are some steps where you can go ahead and check that you have everything.
Once you're done with set up, go ahead and open the REPL either in VS code or on the terminal,
and that will set you up for the next chapter.
Somebody mentioned that in Windows to exit the REPL controls the works. That is the keyboard shortcut.
Somebody in chat so they keep getting Python 3.8.6. That means that they might have an older version
of Python installed. If that is the case, and they went through the steps to install Python 3.9,
they might be able to create their virtual environment or check with the version with another
more specific command. Here in my project folder, I'm going to type deactivate and that will
deactivate the virtual environment that I had activated. Instead of typing this, I don't want
any of you to deactivate your virtual environments. I'm just going to open a new window.
And you'll see here that in my new window, I don't have a virtual environment.
So if you have an older version of Python 3, you should have a Python 3.9 command. I believe in
Windows it's Python 3.9. And that will let you target the more specific version of Python 3 on your system.
There was one other suggestion of potentially using a REPL. It if all else fails.
It was that a good option or not, like bottom line Python owner?
No, because if you want to run Python programs on your system, you want to make sure that you're all set up.
For the person in chat who's on Python 3.8, that's okay. It's a modern enough version of Python 3
that they shouldn't be too far behind. And I'm not going to cover any Python 3.9 specific features
in class today, but they do want to get their environments dialed in. Unfortunately, I'll chat
about this in a little bit, versioning and Python is something that has, there's some history there.
And it's not the easiest thing to do. I imagine that that's where the history of virtual
environments came from originally as to solve some of these problems. So it is possible to have
multiple versions of Python on your machine. And you want to make sure that you're using the right one for your project.